[MEN SHOUTING]
BOY [IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]:
[MAN SINGING lN FOREIGN LANGUAGE
[HAMMERS CLANGING]
MAN [IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]:
[INDlSTlNCT CHATTER]
[HORSE APPROACHlNG]
[COACHMAN SHOUTS
[STONES FALLING]
[DOGS GROWLING]
[RATTLING]
[SCRAPING]
[CRASH FROM ABOVE]
[RATTLING]
[FAINT CRASH]
Sure do love you.
-Morning.
-Good morning, Mrs. MacNeil.
-How are you today?
-Fine, thank you.
That's good.
It's okay, I've got it. Thanks.
-Good morning, madam.
-Good morning, Karl.
Oh, Karl, we've got rats in the attic.
You'd better get some traps.
-Rats?
-I'm afraid so.
But the attic is clean.
All right, then, we've got clean rats.
-No, no. No rats.
-I just heard them, Karl.
Maybe plumbing.
Yeah, or maybe rats.
Now, will you just get the traps?
KARL:
Yes, l go now.
Don't go now.
The stores aren't open yet.
-I'll go see.
-They're closed!
MAN [ON LOUDSPEAKER]:
In the group over here...
...I need a priest, a nun
and two students.
That's what we want.
That's exactly what we want.
[INDlSTlNCT CHATTER]
Burke. Oh, Burke.
-Is this scene really essential?
-Chris.
Just consider if we can do without it.
Take a look at this damn thing.
It just doesn't make sense.
It's plain. You're a teacher of the college.
You don't want the building torn down.
-Come on. I can read, for Christ's sake.
-Well, what's wrong?
Well, why are they tearing
the building down?
Shall we summon the writer?
He's in Paris, l believe.
CHRIS: Hiding?
BURKE: Fucking.
[LAUGHING]
Scene 39: Hotel. Take four.
DIRECTOR:
All right. Hustle, background. And action.
MAN 1 :
Hasn't there been enough killing?
[CROWD CHEERS]
MAN 1 :
Is this your campus?
[CROWD CHEERING]
MAN 1 : Get the Defense Department
off this campus!
[WOMAN SHOUTlNG INDISTINCTLY]
MAN 1 :
It's our school!
-You have no rights!
MAN 2: Hypocrite!
Military complex, man!
DIRECTOR:
And action, Chris.
MAN 1 :
I've seen enough killing in my lifetime!
[CROWD CHEERING]
MAN 1 :
There's no need for it!
WOMAN:
That's right! That's right!
We're all concerned with human rights,
for God's sake...
...but the kids who want
to get an education have a right too!
[CROWD CHEERING]
CHRIS: Don't you understand? It's against
your own principle, for God's sake!
You can't accomplish anything by
shutting kids off from their....
[CROWD SHOUTING]
CHRIS: lf you want-- Hold it, hold it!
MAN: Quiet!
CHRIS: lf you want to effect any change,
you have to do it within the system.
[CROWD BOOING]
DIRECTOR:
Okay, cut. That's a wrap.
-I'll walk home tonight.
-Okay.
Here, take that
and drop it at my house, yeah?
-Good night, Tom.
TOM: Good night.
[CHILDREN LAUGHING]
MAN: There's not a day in my life
that I don't feel like a fraud.
I mean, priests, doctors, lawyers.
I've talked to them all.
[AIRPLANE APPROACHlNG]
I don't know anyone who hasn't
felt that.
[INAUDIBLE DlALOGUE]
CHRIS:
Hello?
In here.
-Hi. How did your day go?
-Oh, not too bad.
It was like the, uh, Walt Disney version
of the Ho Chi Minh story.
Other than that, terrific.
-What we got, anything exciting?
-Here.
-Oh, all right.
-And also, you got an invitation.
-What's this?
-Dinner at the White House.
You're kidding.
Is it a big party or something?
I think it's five or six people.
Oh. Thursday, huh? All right.
REGAN:
Hi, Mom.
CHRIS:
What'd you do today?
-Stuff.
-What's that mean, stuff?
Well, uh, me and Sharon played a game
in the backyard.
-You did.
-And we had a picnic down by the river.
CHRIS:
That sounds good.
You should have seen.
This man came along on this
beautiful gray horse.
-Really? What kind?
-Wasn't he pretty?
Was it a mare, a gelding, what?
-I think it was a gelding.
-Mm-hm.
It was gray. Oh, it was so beautiful.
The guy let me ride it all around
and everything.
-You're kidding.
SHARON: She rode for half an hour.
It was so nice. Oh, I loved it.
Oh, Mom, can't we get a horse?
-Not while we're in Washington, honey.
-Why not, Mom? Ha, ha.
We'll see when we get home, okay?
-When could I have one?
-We'll see, Regan. We'll see.
Hey, listen, on the party invitations,
I wanted to write a personal--
-Regan, don't! Regan, come back here!
-Ha-ha-ha.
[BOTH LAUGHING]
CHRIS: All right, give it up. Give it up!
REGAN: No!
CHRIS: Ooh!
REGAN: Ha-ha-ha.
-You'll be sorry! Come on.
-No!
MAN:
Father?
Could you help an old altar boy?
I'm a Catholic.
BOY 1 :
All right, come on, man.
BOY 2: What, are you crazy?
BOY 1 : Go ahead.
[BOYS SHOUTlNG INDlSTlNCTLY]
[PEOPLE SPEAKING
INDISTINCTLY ON RADIO]
Mama?
Dimmy! Dimmy!
[SPEAKING IN GREEK]
Oh, how are you, Mama?
-I'm so glad to see you.
-You look good.
I'm all right.
-How's your leg?
-How about you? You are all right?
I'm fine, Mama. I'm fine.
[MAN SPEAKING IN GREEK ON RADIO
Your Uncle John passed by to visit me.
KARRAS: Oh, really? When?
-Last month.
-Too tight?
-No.
You have to stay off it. You can't go up and
down the stairs. You have to give it a rest.
Okay.
[SIGHS]
I could take you somewhere where
you'd be safe. You wouldn't be alone.
There would be people around. You
wouldn't be sitting here listening to a radio.
[SPEAKING IN GREEK]
You understand me?
This is my house
and I'm not going no place.
[COUGHS
Dimmy, you worry for something?
-No, Mama.
-You are not happy?
Tell me, what is the matter?
Mama, l'm all right. I'm fine.
Really, I am.
[GREEK MUSIC PLAYING ON RADIO]
Here it comes.
There.
[BOTH LAUGHING]
-Oh, look at that.
-Do you like it?
Aw, isn't that funny? Ha, ha.
I better put him over here to dry, though.
He's still wet.
Oh, here we go.
There, he can dry there.
Hey, where'd this come from?
-I found it.
-Where?
Closet.
Huh.
You been playing with it?
-Yup.
-Do you know how?
I'll show you.
Wait a minute. You need two.
No, you don't. l do it all the time.
Oh, yeah? Well, let's both play with it.
You really don't want me to play, huh?
No, I do. Captain Howdy said no.
-Captain who?
-Captain Howdy.
Who's Captain Howdy?
You know. I make the questions
and he does the answers.
-Oh, Captain Howdy. Yeah, I see.
-He's nice.
Oh, l'll bet he is.
-Here, I'll show you.
-All right.
Captain Howdy,
do you think my mom's pretty?
Captain Howdy?
Captain Howdy, that isn't very nice.
-Well, maybe he's sleeping.
-You think?
Regan, why are you reading that stuff?
Because I like it.
It's not even a good picture of you.
Look at that.
-You look so mature.
-I wouldn't talk.
You wouldn't talk?
Well, I didn't know they were taking it.
I didn't have my makeup man there.
Let me take an eyelash off your face.
Okay. No, I didn't get it.
-Mm.
-What are we gonna do on your birthday?
Isn't it nice it's on Sunday this year?
No work? What can we do?
I don't know.
Well, what would you like to do?
-Got any ideas?
-Mm-mm.
Hmm?
Let me think. Let me think.
What can we do?
Hey, we never finished seeing all the sights
in Washington.
Didn't get to Lee Mansion
and lots of stuff.
Shall we do that? Go sightseeing?
If it's a nice day?
-Yeah, let's do that.
-Okay.
And tomorrow night,
I'll take you to a movie. Okay?
Oh, l love you.
I love you, Rags.
[REGAN GIGGLES]
We'll have a good day, yeah?
You can bring Mr. Dennings, if you like.
Mr. Dennings?
Well, you know, it's okay.
Well, thank you very much...
...but why on earth would I wanna bring
Burke on your birthday?
Well, you like him.
Yeah, l like him. Don't you like him?
Hey, what's going on? What is this?
-You're gonna marry him, aren't you?
-Oh, my God. Are you kidding?
-What?
-Me marry Burke Dennings?
Don't be silly. Of course not.
Where did you ever get an idea like that?
But you like him.
Of course I like him. I like pizzas too,
but I'm not gonna marry one.
You don't like him like Daddy?
Regan, I love your daddy.
I'll always love your daddy, honey.
Okay? Burke just comes
around here a lot, because...
[SIGHS]
...well, he's lonely.
He don't got nothing to do.
Well, I heard differently.
Oh, you did? What did you hear, huh?
-I don't know. I just thought.
-Come on. What did you hear?
Well, you didn't think so good.
-How do you know? Ha, ha.
-Ha-ha-ha.
Because Burke and l are just friends.
Okay? Really.
Okay.
You ready for sleep?
-Good night.
-Good night, honey.
[ON RADlO]
Lord, I was born a ramblin' man
[CROWD CHATTERING]
KARRAS:
It's my mother, Tom.
She's alone. I never should have left her.
At least in New York, I'd be near her.
I'd be close to her.
I could see about a transfer, Damien.
I need reassignment, Tom. I want out of
this job. It's wrong, it's no good.
You're the best we've got.
Am l really?
It's more than psychiatry,
and you know that, Tom.
Some of their problems come down
to faith...
...their vocation, the meaning of their lives,
and I can't cut it anymore.
I need out. I'm unfit.
Think I've lost my faith, Tom.
Hello?
Yes, this is Mrs. MacNeil.
Operator, you have got to be kidding!
I have been on this line for 20 minutes!
Jesus Christ. Can you believe this?
He doesn't even call his daughter
on her birthday.
-Maybe the circuit is busy.
-Oh, circuits, my ass!
He doesn't give a shit.
-Why don't you let me--?
-No, I've got it, Sharon. It's all right.
Yes. No, operator,
don't tell me there's no answer.
It's the Hotel Excelsior in Rome.
Would you try it again, please,
and let it ring?
Hello? Yes.
No, operator,
I've given you the number four times.
Do you take an illiteracy test to get
that job, for Christ's sakes?
Don't tell me to be calm, goddamn it!
[RlNGING]
Yeah?
You're kidding me.
Okay. I thought I just went to bed.
Yeah.
Hey, what are we doing, scene 61 ?
Okay. Oh, just remind Flo about
that blue belt, huh?
All right. Yeah, I'll see you.
What are you doing here?
My bed was shaking.
I can't get to sleep.
Oh, honey.
[RATTLING]
[SCRAPING FROM ABOVE]
[SCRAPING]
[CLATTERING]
Goddamn it.
Jesus.
[SCRAPING]
[YELLS]
KARL:
There's nothing.
Oh, Karl.
Jesus Christ, Karl, don't do that.
Very sorry, but you see, no rats.
No rats. Thanks a lot. That's terrific.
[BELL RINGING
Oh, my God.
[LAUGHING]
NURSE:
Okay. Unroll your fist.
Arm up.
Very good. That wasn't so bad, was it?
Remain perfectly still. Breathe normally.
DOCTOR:
Tell me if you feel a vibration.
Regan?
You feel anything?
Can you feel this?
I don't feel anything.
Put this in your mouth.
Keep it there.
This tells your temperature.
When the red light goes on,
that's your temperature.
I don't want it.
[REGAN HUMMING]
A disorder of the nerves.
At least we think it is.
We don't know yet exactly how it works.
It's often seen in early adolescence.
She shows all the symptoms.
Hyperactivity.
Her temper.
Performance in math.
CHRIS:
Yeah. Why the math? What is that?
It affects her concentration.
CHRIS:
Ah-ha.
-Now, this is for Ritalin.
-Okay.
Ten milligrams a day.
Is that a tranquilizer?
It's a stimulant.
A stimulant? My God,
she's higher than a kite now.
Her condition isn't quite what it seems.
Nobody knows the cause of hyperkinetic
behavior in a child.
The Ritalin seems to work
to relieve the condition.
And as to how or why,
we really don't know.
But, uh, her symptoms could be
overreaction to depression.
That's out of my field.
My daughter isn't depressed.
Well, you mentioned her father
and the separation.
You think I should take her
to a psychiatrist?
No. I think we should wait
and see what happens with the Ritalin.
I think that's the answer.
-Okay.
-Let's wait two, three weeks.
All right. And the lies she's been telling?
That's part of it, huh?
-Lies?
-Like saying her bed's shaking. That stuff.
Have you ever known your daughter
to swear?
-To use obscenities?
-No, never.
Hmm. Interesting.
Similar-- Similar to things like her lying...
-...it's uncharacteristic for her.
-I don't understand. She doesn't swear.
Well, she let loose quite a string
while I was examining her, Mrs. MacNeil.
I find that hard to believe.
What did she say?
Her vocabulary is rather extensive.
Well, give me an example. Like what?
Specifically, what did she say?
Specifically, Mrs. MacNeil...
...she advised me to keep my fingers
away from her...
...goddamn cunt.
I can't believe it.
[LAUGHS]
-She--
-You don't think a psychiatrist...?
No. I think the best explanation
is always the simplest.
-Well, we'll wait. We'll wait and see.
-Yeah.
So in the meantime...
...try not to worry.
How?
The edema affected her brain,
you understand?
She don't let no doctor come near her.
She was all the time screaming,
talking to the radio.
-You should've called me when it happened.
-Listen.
Regular hospital not gonna
put up with that.
We give her a shot and bring her here...
...until the doctors fix up her leg,
then we take her right out.
Two or three months and she's out,
good as new.
-Miss?
-Yes?
We want to see Mrs. Karras.
-Do you have an appointment?
-Yes.
-Are you a relative?
-Yes, I am her brother. He is her son.
Just a minute.
[WOMAN CRYING]
You know, it's funny.
If you wasn't a priest, you'd be famous
psychiatrist on Park Avenue.
Your mother, she'd be living in a penthouse
instead of there.
You go in, Dimmy.
I'll wait for you outside.
You'll find Mrs. Karras in the last bed
on the left-hand side.
No, no. No, no.
Go get someone else.
Don't bother the father.
Go to your bed. Go to your bed.
[MUTTERING
No, no. No, no.
The father will be back to see you.
It's all right.
Mama.
It's Dimmy, Mama.
Dimmy.
Why you did this to me, Dimmy?
Why?
Come on,
I'm gonna take you out of here, Mama.
I'm gonna take you home.
I'll get you out of here tonight, Mama.
[YELLING IN GREEK]
Mama, everything's gonna be all right.
Mama, l'm gonna take you home.
-Couldn't you have put her someplace else?
-Like what? Private hospital?
Who got the money for that, Dimmy?
You?
[GRUNTING
[CHATTERING]
There seems to be an alien pubic hair
in my drink.
-I beg your pardon?
-Never seen it before in my life. Have you?
We're pretty comfortable up there compared
to the Gemini and Mercury programs.
They were tight for space.
You see, we got about 21 0 cubic feet,
so we can move around.
If you ever go up there again,
will you take me along?
Ha-ha-ha. What for?
First missionary on Mars.
Tell me, was it public relations you did
for the Gestapo or community relations?
-I'm Swiss.
-Yes, of course.
And you never went bowling with Goebbels,
either, I suppose, eh?
Nazi bastard.
Over behind the church.
You know where I mean?
-It's a red brick wing.
-Saint Mike's.
What goes on there?
Who's the priest I keep seeing there?
He's there all the time. He has black hair.
He's very intense looking. Who's that?
-Damien Karras.
-Karras?
That's his office, back of Saint Mike's.
He's our-- Our psychiatric counselor.
He had a pretty rough knock last night,
poor guy. His mother passed away.
She was living by herself...
...and l guess she was dead
a couple of days before they found her.
Cunting Hun.
Bloody, damned, butchering Nazi pig.
[YELLING]
KARL:
Stop it! l'll kill you!
[BOTH SHOUTlNG INDlSTlNCTLY]
What's the matter with you?
What's for dessert?
You sleeping?
You get some sleep.
[BABBLlNG]
CHRIS:
Okay. Very good. All right.
Listen, Burke, your car's at the curb.
Louie's waiting. It's nice and warm.
Yes, honey. What?
Fuck it.
[GUESTS SINGING lNDlSTlNCTLY]
[LAUGHING]
-I've never seen him acting up.
-Really. Blind is what he was.
[SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
ALL [SlNGING]:
Down on Thoity-Thoid and Thoid
-Hi, Chris. This is a great party.
-Yeah, don't stop. Keep going.
I don't need any encouragement. My idea
of heaven is a solid white nightclub...
...with me as a headliner for all eternity,
and they love me.
[ALL LAUGH]
ALL [SlNGING]:
Down on the east side
Of Thoity-Thoid and Thoid
That's my home sweet home
Some people think
It's the home of black eyes
Just because--
Hey, I think we've got a guest.
You're gonna die up there.
Regan?
Oh, my God, honey.
Honey, what's the matter?
-Sorry, she's sick.
-It's okay.
She didn't know what she was saying.
Come upstairs. Come on.
What made you say that, Regan?
Do you know, sweetheart?
REGAN:
Mother?
What's wrong with me?
It's just like the doctor said.
It's nerves, and that's all. Okay?
You just take your pills
and you'll be fine. Really.
Okay?
Is it coming out, Willi?
-Yes, I think so.
-Good.
[REGAN SCREAMS]
[BANGING]
REGAN:
Mother! Mother!
[GASPS]
-Oh, my God!
-Make it stop!
[SCREAMING]
MAN 1 : I'm gonna fold.
MAN 2: Big flop.
Another five for the pair.
There's the ten with two and three of clubs.
And a six. Pair of threes still best.
MAN 3: I'll talk to you about it tomorrow.
MAN 4: Yeah!
KARRAS:
Yeah.
MAN 4: Hey, if you get a chance,
can you take a look at it for me?
KARRAS: Where'd you get the money
for the Chivas Regal...
-...the poor box?
-Ha.
That's an insult. I got a vow of poverty.
Where'd you get it, then?
I stole it.
I believe you.
College presidents shouldn't drink.
Tends to set a bad example.
I figure I saved him from
a big temptation.
Oh, Christ!
I should have been there. I wasn't there.
Should have been.
There was nothing you could do.
Lie down.
Give me the butt. Come on.
-Now you think you can sleep?
-Yeah.
-Are you gonna steal my shoes now?
-No.
I tell fortunes by reading the creases.
Now, shut up and go to sleep.
Good night.
KARRAS:
Stealing is a sin.
[KARRAS MOANS]
[INAUDIBLE DlALOGUE]
[SCREAMING]
I don't want it!
-Regan, honey, it's to help you.
-I don't want it!
-Hold still, honey.
You fucking bastard!
Remember also, O Lord,
thy servant, Mary Karras...
...who has gone before us with the sign of
faith and sleeps the sleep of peace.
ALL:
Lord, l am not worthy to receive you.
But only say the word
and I shall be healed.
May the body of Christ bring me
to everlasting life.
Well, it's a symptom...
...of a type of disturbance in
the chemical-electrical activity of the brain.
In your daughter's case, the temporal lobe,
up here in the lateral part of the brain.
-Mm-hm.
-It's rare...
...but it does cause bizarre
hallucinations...
...and usually just before a convulsion.
A convulsion?
The shaking of the bed.
That's doubtless due to muscular spasms.
Oh, no, no, that was no spasm.
Look, l got on the bed.
The whole bed was thumping
and rising off the floor...
...and shaking, the whole thing,
with me on it.
Mrs. MacNeil, the problem
with your daughter is not her bed.
It's her brain.
So, um, ahem. What causes this?
Lesion. Lesion in the temporal lobe.
It's a kind of seizure disorder.
Look, Doc, I really don't understand how
her whole personality could change.
-In the temporal lobe, it's very common.
-It is?
It, uh, can last for days, even weeks.
It isn't rare to find destructive...
...even criminal behavior.
Hey, do me a favor, will you?
Tell me something good.
Don't be alarmed. lf it's a lesion,
in a way, she's fortunate.
All we have to do is remove the scar.
-Let's move her.
MAN: Regan, can you sit up, scoot over?
A little more.
Good.
Regan, I'm just gonna move you down
on the table, okay?
NURSE:
Let me do this.
It's okay.
See? There we go.
MAN:
It's just for a short time.
NURSE:
You're doing fine.
MAN:
Very sticky.
Good. Now, Regan, you're gonna feel
something a little bit cold and wet.
Okay. Now you're gonna feel
a little stick here. Don't move.
[GRUNTS
Good.
Okay. You're gonna feel
some pressure here. Now, don't move.
[GASPS]
[GROANING]
MAN:
Hook up.
[MACHlNE CLANGING]
[GASPS]
DOCTOR:
There's nothing there.
No vascular displacement at all.
Do you want me to run another series?
I don't think so.
I'd like you to see her again.
Excuse me, doctor.
Chris MacNeil is on the phone.
She says it's urgent.
-You got some time?
-Of course.
[DOORBELL BUZZING]
[REGAN SCREAMING]
-Dr. Klein?
-Yes, I'm Dr. Klein.
-This is Dr. Taney.
-How do you do?
Things have gotten worse since l phoned.
Come upstairs.
-Is she having spasms again?
-They've gotten violent.
-Did you give her the medication?
-Yes.
-What was that?
-Thorazine.
Before that, it was Ritalin.
[REGAN SCREAMING]
Chris, doctors.
-This is Dr. Taney.
REGAN: Mother, please!
CHRIS: What is it?
-Please, make it stop!
It's burning! It's burning!
CHRIS:
Do something, doctor. Please, help her.
Please, Mother, make it stop!
He's trying to kill me!
Mother! Mother!
[GROWLING]
[GROANS]
All right, Regan,
let's see what the trouble--
CHRIS:
Regan!
[IN DEMONIC VOICE
Keep away! The sow is mine!
Fuck me! Fuck me! Fuck me!
[SCREAMING]
[SCREAMS]
REGAN:
Stay away from me! Stay away!
TANEY:
Hold her steady. Hold her tight!
REGAN:
Don't let them!
[CRYING
[REGAN SCREAMING]
She's heavily sedated.
She'll probably sleep through tomorrow.
What was going on in there?
How could she fly off the bed like that?
Pathological states can induce
abnormal strength...
...accelerated motor performance.
For example...
...say a 90-pound woman sees her child
pinned under the wheel of a truck...
...runs out and lifts the wheels
a half a foot up off the ground.
You've heard the story. Same thing here.
Same principle, I mean.
So, what's wrong with her?
We still think that the temporal lobe--
Oh, what are you talking about,
for Christ's sakes?
Did you see her or not?
She's acting like she's fucking
out of her mind!
Psychotic, like a split personality, or....
Oh, Jesus, I'm sorry.
There haven't been more than
1 00 authentic cases...
...of so-called "split personality,"
Mrs. MacNeil.
Now, l know the temptation is
to leap to psychiatry...
...but any reasonable psychiatrist would
exhaust the somatic possibilities first.
So, what's next?
A pneumoencephalogram,
I would think, to pin down that lesion.
It will involve another spinal.
Oh, Christ!
Well, what we missed in the EEG
and the arteriograms...
...could conceivably turn up there.
At least it would eliminate certain
other possibilities.
[GROANING]
KLEIN:
Dr. Taney says the x-rays are negative.
In other words, normal.
You keep any drugs in your house?
No, of course not. Nothing like that.
Are you sure?
Well, of course, l'm sure.
I'd tell you.
Christ, I don't even smoke grass.
Are you planning to be home soon?
I mean, uh, to L.A., l mean.
Um....
No, I, uh--
I'm building a new house.
My old one has been sold.
I don't know.
I was gonna take....
I was gonna take Regan to Europe
for a while after she finished school.
Why do you ask?
I think it's time we started looking
for a psychiatrist.
[SIREN WAILING]
[PHONE RINGING]
Hello?
Sharon?
Shit.
God.
Sharon!
What do you mean,
leaving Regan by herself?
[DOORBELL BUZZING]
Her window's wide open.
The room is freezing.
-Didn't he tell you?
-Who?
-Burke is--
-What's Burke got to do with it?
Nobody was here.
When I went to get the Thorazine...
-...I had him stay with her, and....
-Oh.
-I should have known better. Sorry.
-I guess you should have.
How were the tests?
We have to start looking for a shrink.
Hi, Chuck. Come on in.
I suppose you heard.
Heard what?
You haven't heard.
Burke's dead.
He must have been drunk. He fell from
the top of the steps right outside.
By the time he hit M Street,
he broke his neck.
CHRIS:
Oh, God.
[SOBS
No!
Yeah, l know.
[CRYING
Sharon--
Oh, my God.
[SCREAMING]
PSYCHIATRIST: When l touch
your forehead, open your eyes.
Are you comfortable, Regan?
Yes.
How old are you?
Twelve.
Is there someone inside you?
Sometimes.
Who is it?
I don't know.
Is it Captain Howdy?
If I ask him to tell me,
will you let him answer?
No.
PSYCHIATRIST:
Why not?
I'm afraid.
PSYCHIATRIST:
If he talks to me, I think he'll leave you.
Do you want him to leave you?
Yes.
I'm speaking to the person
inside of Regan now.
If you are there, you, too, are hypnotized
and must answer all my questions.
Come forward...
...and answer me now.
[CHRlS GASPS]
[REGAN GROWLlNG]
[COUGHING
Are you the person inside of Regan?
Who are you?
[GROWLS]
[SCREAMING]
-Help me!
KLEIN: Let go!
[SCREAMING]
Father Karras?
Have we met?
No, we haven't met,
but they said I could tell.
That you look like a boxer.
William F. Kinderman. Homicide.
What's this all about?
It's true. You do look like a boxer.
Like John Garfield in Body and Soul.
Exactly. John Garfield.
People tell you that, Father?
Do people tell you
you look like Paul Newman?
Always.
Well, you know this director
who was doing the film here...
...Burke Dennings?
I've seen him.
You've seen him.
You're also familiar how last week
he died?
Only what I read in the papers.
Father, what do you know on
the subject of witchcraft?
From the witching end, not the hunting.
I once did a paper on it.
Really?
From the psychiatric end.
I know. I read it.
All of this desecration in the church...
...do you think this has anything to do
with witchcraft?
Maybe. Some rituals used in
the black mass, maybe.
And now Dennings.
You read how he died?
In a fall.
Let me tell you how.
And please, Father...
...confidential.
Burke Dennings, good Father...
...was found at the bottom of those steps
leading to M Street...
...with his head turned completely
around...
...facing backwards.
Didn't happen in the fall?
It's possible.
-Possible, however--
-Unlikely.
Exactly.
So on the one hand,
we've got a witchcraft kind of murder...
...and on the other hand, a black mass-type
desecration in the church.
You think the killer
and the desecrator are the same?
Maybe somebody crazy...
...somebody with a spite against
the Church.
Some unconscious rebellion.
KARRAS:
A sick priest, is that it?
Look, Father, this is hard for you.
Please, I understand...
...but for priests on the campus here,
you're the psychiatrist.
You'd know who was sick at the time,
who wasn't.
I mean, this kind of sickness,
you'd know that.
I don't know anyone who fits
that description.
Ah.
Doctor's ethics.
If you knew, you wouldn't tell, huh?
No, I probably wouldn't.
Not to bother you with trivia,
but a psychiatrist...
...in sunny California, no less...
...was put in jail for not telling the police
what he knew about a patient.
-Is that a threat?
-No, I mention it only in passing.
Incidentally,
I mention it only in passing...
...I could always tell the judge it was
a matter of confession.
[CHUCKLING]
Hey, Father, wait a minute.
-Do you like movies?
-Very much.
Well, I get passes
to the best shows in town.
Mrs. K, though, you know,
she gets tired, never likes to go.
-That's too bad.
-Yeah, I hate to go alone.
I love to talk film...
...discuss, to critique.
You want to see a film with me?
I got passes to the Crest. It's Othello.
-Who's in it?
Debbie Reynolds, Desdemona,
and Othello, Groucho Marx. You happy?
-I've seen it.
-Ah.
One last time. You can think
of some priest who fits the bill?
-Come on.
-No, answer the question, Father Paranoia.
All right. All right.
-You know who I think really did it?
-Who?
The Dominicans. Go pick on them.
I could have you deported,
you know that?
I lied.
You look like Sal Mineo.
BARRlNGER: It looks like a type of disorder
that's, uh, rarely ever seen anymore...
...except in primitive cultures.
We call it, uh,
somnambular-form possession.
Quite frankly, we really don't know
much about it at all...
...except that it starts with a conflict
or a guilt...
...and it leads to the patient's delusions
that his body has been invaded...
...by some alien intelligence. Um....
A spirit, if you will.
Look, l'm telling you again,
and you'd better believe me...
...I am not going to lock her up
in some goddamn asylum.
-Well, it's out of--
-And I don't care what you call it.
I'm not putting her away.
Well, I'm sorry.
You're sorry? Jesus Christ!
Eighty-eight doctors, and all you can
tell me with all your bullshit is....
Of course, there is one outside chance
for a cure.
But, um, I think of it
as a shock treatment.
As l said, it's a very outside chance--
Would you just name it, for God's sakes?
What is it?
-Do you have any religious beliefs?
CHRIS: No.
What about your daughter?
No. Why?
Have you ever heard of exorcism?
Well, it's a stylized ritual...
...in which the, uh, rabbi or the priest try
to drive out the so-called invading spirit.
It's been pretty much discarded
these days...
...except by the Catholics, who keep it
in the closet as a sort of embarrassment.
But it, uh, has worked, in fact...
...although not for the reasons they think,
of course.
It's purely force of suggestion.
The, uh-- The victim's belief in possession
is what helped cause it...
...so in that same way...
...the belief in the power of exorcism
can make it disappear.
You're telling me that I should
take my daughter to a witch doctor.
Is that it?
Karl?
Did you put this in Regan's bedroom?
She's going to be well?
Karl, if you put this in Regan's bedroom,
I want you to tell me. Now, did you?
No, not me.
I didn't.
This was under Regan's pillow.
Did you put it there?
Of course, I didn't.
I didn't put it.
[KNOCKING ON DOOR
KARL: Excuse me, madam.
-What?
-A man to see you.
CHRIS: What man?
KINDERMAN:
Might your daughter remember, perhaps...
...if Mr. Dennings was in her room
that night?
-Why do you ask?
-Mm.
Might she remember?
No, she was heavily sedated.
It's serious?
Yes, l'm afraid it is.
-May I ask...?
-We still don't know.
Watch out for drafts.
A draft in the fall when the house is hot
is a magic carpet for bacteria.
Excuse me, madam. Anything else?
No, Karl, we're fine. Thank you.
It's all right, Karl.
Why are you asking all this?
It's strange.
The deceased comes to visit,
stays only 20 minutes...
...and leaves all alone a very sick girl.
And speaking plainly, Mrs. MacNeil...
...it isn't likely he would fall
from a window.
Besides, a fall wouldn't do to his neck
what we found.
Except maybe one chance in a thousand.
No. My hunch....
My opinion...
...he was killed by a very powerful man:
point one.
And the fracturing of his skull: point two...
...plus the various other things
we mentioned...
...would make it very probable...
...probable, not certain...
...that the deceased was killed and
then pushed from your daughter's window.
But nobody was in the room
except your daughter, so how can this be?
It could be one way.
If someone came calling
between the time Miss Spencer left...
...and the time you returned.
Judas Priest, just a second.
-The servants? They have visitors?
-Not at all.
You were expecting a package that day,
some delivery?
Not that l know of.
Groceries, cleaning, uh, a package?
I really wouldn't know.
See, Karl takes care of all that.
I see.
Would you like to ask him?
No, never mind, it's....
It's very remote.
No, never mind.
Yeah.
Would you like some more coffee?
Please.
[CHUCKLES]
That's cute.
Your daughter, she's the artist?
-Thank you.
-You're welcome.
Incidentally, um...
...you might ask your daughter...
...if she remembers seeing Mr. Dennings
in her room that night.
Look, he wouldn't have any reason
in the world to go up to her room.
Oh, l know, l realize...
...but if certain British doctors never asked,
"What is this fungus?"...
...we wouldn't today have penicillin.
Correct?
Well, when she's better, I'll ask her.
-Yeah, couldn't hurt.
-Okay.
Uh, in the meantime....
That's okay.
-I really hate to ask you this, but--
-What?
For my daughter,
could you please give an autograph?
Of course. Uh, where's a pencil?
Right here. Here.
Oh.
She'd love it.
And what's her name?
I lied. lt's for me.
[CHRlS CHUCKLES]
-The spelling is on the back: Kinderman.
-Okay.
You know that film you made, um, AngeI?
-Oh, yeah.
-I saw that six times.
-Really?
-It was beautiful.
Ha, ha. Thank you.
You're a very nice lady.
-Thank you.
-You're a nice man.
Uh, I'll come back
when she's feeling better.
-Bye.
REGAN:
Please, no!
DEMONlC VOICE: Do it!
REGAN: Please, don't!
DEMONlC VOICE:
You bitch! Do it! Do it!
REGAN:
Please, no!
[SCREAMING]
REGAN [IN DEMONIC VOICE]:
Yes! Let Jesus fuck you!
Let Jesus fuck you! Let him fuck you!
[BOTH GRUNTING]
Aah!
Give it! Give it to me! Aah!
-Ugh!
-Lick me! Lick me!
[COUGHS
[GRUNTS
[SCREAMS]
SHARON:
Chris!
Mrs. MacNeil, open the door!
[BANGING ON DOOR]
Open the door!
[AS BURKE]
Do you know what she did...
...your cunting daughter?
[SCREAMING]
Chris MacNeil?
Please, go away.
I'm Father Karras.
I'm very sorry. Hello.
I should have told you
I wouldn't be in uniform.
Yeah, that would have helped.
-Have you got a cigarette, Father?
-Sure.
Thanks.
Cold.
Yeah.
Uh--
How did a shrink ever get to be a priest?
It's the other way around. The Society
sent me through medical school.
Oh.
Where?
Harvard, Bellevue, Johns Hopkins.
-Places like that.
-I see.
-You're a friend of Father Dyer's, right?
-Yes, I am.
-Pretty close?
-Pretty close.
Did he talk to you about my party?
He sure did.
About my daughter?
No, I didn't know you had one.
-He didn't mention her?
-No.
Oh.
Didn't tell you what she did?
He didn't mention her.
Priests are pretty tight-mouthed,
then, huh?
That depends.
-On what?
-The priest.
Sure.
I mean, what if a person,
uh, came to you...
...you know, that was a murderer
or criminal of some kind...
...and they wanted some kind of help?
I mean, would you have to turn him in?
Well, if he came to me for spiritual advice,
I'd say no.
-You wouldn't?
-No, I wouldn't.
But I would try to convince him
to turn himself in.
Mm-hm.
And, uh, how do you go about
getting an exorcism?
I beg your pardon?
If, um-- If a person's, you know,
possessed by a demon, or something...
...how do they get an exorcism?
I'd have to get them into a time machine
and get them back to the 1 6th century.
I didn't get you.
It just doesn't happen anymore,
Mrs. MacNeil.
Oh, yeah? Since when?
Well, since we learned about mental illness,
paranoia, schizophrenia.
All those things they taught me
at Harvard.
Mrs. MacNeil,
since the day l joined the Jesuits...
...I've never met one priest
who has performed an exorcism. Not one.
Yeah, well...
[CLEARS THROAT]
...it just so happens that somebody
very close to me...
...is probably possessed.
And needs an exorcist.
Father Karras, it's my little girl.
[SOBS
Then that's all the more reason
to forget about exorcism.
Why? I don't understand.
-To begin with, it could make things worse.
-Oh, how?
Secondly, the Church,
before it approves an exorcism...
...conducts an investigation to see if
it's warranted. That takes time.
-Yeah, but--
-Meanwhile, your daughter--
-You could do it yourself.
-No. I'd need Church approval...
-...and that's rarely given.
-But-- Uh....
-Could you see her?
-Yes, I could.
I could see her as a psychiatrist, but l--
Oh, not a psychiatrist. She needs a priest.
She's seen every fucking psychiatrist
in the world, and they sent me to you.
Now are you gonna send me
back to them?
-Jesus Christ, won't somebody help me?
-You don't understand--
Oh, God, can't you help her?
Just help her!
[CRYING
[REGAN GROANING
It wants no straps.
KARRAS:
Hello, Regan.
I'm a friend of your mother's.
I'd like to help you.
[IN DEMONIC VOICE
You might loosen these straps, then.
I'm afraid you might hurt yourself,
Regan.
I'm not Regan.
I see.
Well, then, let's introduce ourselves.
I'm Damien Karras.
And l'm the devil.
Now, kindly undo these straps.
If you're the devil,
why not make the straps disappear?
That's much too vulgar a display
of power, Karras.
Where's Regan?
In here, with us.
Show me Regan
and I'll loosen one of the straps.
[AS OLD MAN]
Could you help an old altar boy, Father?
[IN DEMONIC VOICE
Your mother's in here with us, Karras.
Would you like to leave a message?
I'll see that she gets it.
If that's true...
...then you must know my mother's
maiden name.
What is it?
[ROARS]
[YELLS]
[COUGHING
Thank you.
Look, l'm only against the possibility of
doing your daughter more harm than good.
Nothing you could do
could make it any worse.
I can't do it.
I need evidence that the Church
would accept...
-...as signs of possession.
-Like what?
Speaking in a language
she's never known or studied.
What else?
I don't know. l'd have to look it up.
I thought you were supposed
to be an expert.
There are no experts.
You probably know as much about
possession as most priests.
Look, your daughter doesn't say
she's a demon.
She says she's the devil himself.
If you've seen as many psychotics
as I have...
...you'd realize that's the same thing
as saying you're Napoleon Bonaparte.
You asked me what I think is best
for your daughter.
Six months under observation
in the best hospital you can find.
You show me Regan's double...
...same face, same voice, everything...
...and l'd know it wasn't Regan.
I'd know in my gut.
I'm telling you that that thing upstairs
isn't my daughter.
I want you to tell me that you know
for a fact...
...that there's nothing wrong
with my daughter except in her mind.
Tell me you know for a fact
that an exorcism wouldn't do any good.
You tell me that!
Did Regan know a priest was
coming over?
-No.
-Did you know my mother died recently?
-Yes, I did. l'm very sorry.
-No.
Is Regan aware of it?
Not at all.
Why do you ask?
It's not important. Good night.
REGAN [ON RECORDER]:
Hello?
[CHRlS SPEAKlNG INDISTINCTLY
ON RECORDER]
CHRIS: Here, take it and just don't....
REGAN: Okay. Um.
Hello, Daddy?
This is me.
-What should l say? l don't know.
CHRIS: Just talk to your daddy.
-Anything you want.
REGAN: All right, um....
CHRIS: Tell him what you've been doing
and how you're feeling and like that.
REGAN:
Uh....
Well, you see, um--
l mean, I hope you can hear me.
Can you hear me okay?
-Well, uh, let me see.
CHRIS: He's not gonna answer you.
REGAN:
Uh, ha-ha-ha.
CHRIS: Go on. Talk to your daddy, honey.
REGAN: Um....
l don't know what to say, though. Um--
Well, let's see. First we-- No.
-Wait. l don't know.
CHRIS: Come on, Regan.
-Tell him about Washington.
REGAN: Okay.
See, we're in Washington now,
Daddy, and....
He broke the bread,
gave it to his disciples and said:
"Take this, all of you, and eat it...
...for this is my body."
When the supper was ended,
he took the cup.
Again he gave you thanks and praise.
He gave the cup to his disciples and said,
"Take this...
...all of you, and drink from it.
This is the cup of my blood.
The blood of the new and everlasting
covenant, the mystery of faith."
[IN DEMONIC VOICE
What an excellent day for an exorcism.
You'd like that?
Intensely.
But wouldn't that drive you
out of Regan?
It would bring us together.
You and Regan?
You and us.
[MOANS]
-Did you do that?
-Uh-huh.
-Do it again.
-In time.
No, now.
In time.
Mirabile dictu, don't you agree?
You speak Latin?
[BOTH SPEAKlNG IN LATIN]
[SPEAKS IN FRENCH
[SPEAKS IN LATIN
How long are you planning
to stay in Regan?
Until she rots and lies stinking
in the earth.
What's that?
Holy water.
You keep it away.
[SCREAMS]
It burns!
Oh, it burns!
[SCREAMING]
[SPEAKING GIBBERISH]
[GROWLS]
[CONTINUES SPEAKING GIBBERISH]
Who are you?
[SCREAMING]
CHRIS:
You know, I'm, like, in seclusion.
No, I'm just exhausted from work.
Um....
She's-- She's all right.
She's just a little....
I don't want to talk about it, okay?
Um--
Okay, I'll talk to you.
I'll call you as soon as it's over, all right?
No, I just-- I'm really--
I'm going through something...
...and l just have to, uh....
No, no. No, no.
There's nothing.
Hey, thanks a lot.
Bye, now.
-Want a drink?
-Please.
What do you drink?
Uh, Scotch.
-Ice, water.
-Okay.
No ice. I'll get some from the kitchen.
-No, I'll take it straight.
-It's fine.
No, please, sit.
-Really? You sure?
-Yeah, sit.
Where's her father?
In Europe.
-Have you told him what's happening?
-No.
Well, I think you should.
I told Regan that was holy water. I sprinkled
it on her and she reacted very violently.
It's tap water.
What's the difference?
Holy water's blessed. And that doesn't
help support a case for possession.
She killed Burke Dennings.
What?
She pushed him out her window.
[REGAN SPEAKING GIBBERISH
ON RECORDER]
KARRAS:
Who are you?
[REGAN CONTINUES
SPEAKING GIBBERISH]
It's a language, all right. It's English.
What do you mean?
It's English in reverse. Listen.
DEMONlC VOICE:
Give us time.
Let her die.
DEMONlC VOICE [ON RECORDER]:
l am no one. l am no one.
Fear the priest.
[GROWL]
Merrin!
[TAPE REWlNDING]
l am no one.
Merrin! Fear the priest.
[PHONE RINGING]
Merrin!
Yeah?
I'll be right there.
I don't want Chris to see this.
-Well, what's wrong? What is it?
-Shh.
You're convinced that it's genuine?
I don't know.
No, not really, l suppose.
But I have made...
...a prudent judgment that it meets
the conditions set down in The Ritual.
You would want to do the exorcism
yourself?
Yes.
Might be best to have a man
with experience.
Maybe someone who's spent time
in foreign missions.
I understand, Your Excellency.
Let's see who's around.
In the meantime,
I'll call you as soon as l know.
Thank you, Your Excellency.
Well, he does know the background.
I doubt there's any danger in just
having him assist.
There should be a psychiatrist present,
anyway.
What about the exorcist?
Have you any ideas?
How about Lankester Merrin?
Merrin?
I had a notion he was in Iraq.
I read he was working on a dig
near Nineveh.
You're right, but he's finished.
He came back three or four months ago.
He's at Woodstock now.
What's he doing there, teaching?
He's working on another book.
Don't you think he's too old, Tom?
How's his health?
He must be all right.
He's still running around digging up tombs.
Mm.
-Besides, he's had experience.
-I didn't know that.
Ten, 1 2 years ago, l think, in Africa.
The exorcism supposedly lasted months.
I heard it damn near killed him.
Father?
-You're Mrs. MacNeil?
-Yes.
I'm Father Merrin.
-Come in.
-Thank you.
-Is Father Karras here?
-Yes.
-He's here already.
-Father?
-Father Karras.
-It's an honor to meet you, Father.
[DEMONIC VOICE SCREAMING]
-Are you very tired?
-No.
I'd like you to go quickly across
to the Residence, Damien...
...and gather up a cassock for myself...
...two surplices, a purple stole,
and some holy water...
...and, um...
...your copy of The Roman Ritual.
The large one.
I believe we should begin.
Do you want to hear the background
of the case first?
Why?
MAN [ON RADIO]:
This is yours to do with as you please.
You can choose to escape, if you want,
but you may never be able to return.
Don't let anyone decide for you.
[REGAN MOANING]
Hail Mary, full of grace....
[PRAYING INDISTINCTLY]
-Excuse me.
-Thank you.
Thank you very much.
You're welcome.
Would you like some brandy in that,
Father?
Well, the doctors say l shouldn't.
But thank God...
...my will is weak.
MERRIN: Especially important is the warning
to avoid conversations with the demon.
We may ask what is relevant,
but anything beyond that is dangerous.
He's a liar. The demon is a liar.
He will lie to confuse us.
But he will also mix lies with the truth...
...to attack us.
The attack is psychological, Damien.
And powerful.
So don't listen.
Remember that. Do not listen.
It might be helpful
if l gave you some background...
...on the different personalities Regan
has manifested.
So far, I'd say there seem to be three.
-She's convinced that she's--
-There is only one.
[REGAN MOANING]
What is your daughter's middle name,
Mrs. MacNeil?
Teresa.
What a lovely name.
[IN DEMONIC VOICE
Stick your cock up her ass...
...you motherfucking
worthless cocksucker.
-Be silent!
-Aah!
[SCREAMING]
Our Father, who art in heaven...
...hallowed be thy name.
Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done...
...on earth as it is in heaven.
Give us this day our daily bread.
Forgive us our trespasses...
...as we forgive those who trespass
against us.
And lead us not into temptation.
But deliver us from the evil one.
Save me, O God, by thy name.
By thy might, defend my cause.
[SCREAMS]
Proud men have risen up against me,
and men of violence seek my life...
...but God is my helper
and the Lord sustains my life.
In every need, he has delivered me.
Glory be to the Father,
to the Son and to the Holy Spirit.
As it was in the beginning,
is now and shall be, world without end.
-Save your servant.
-Who places her trust in thee, my God.
-Be unto her, O Lord, a fortified tower.
-In the face of the enemy....
[SCREAMS]
-Let the enemy have no power over her.
-Son of Iniquity be powerless to harm her.
Your mother sucks cocks in hell, Karras.
You faithless slime.
The Lord be with you.
-And also with you.
-Let us pray.
Holy Lord, almighty Father...
[YELLING]
...everlasting God...
...and Father of our Lord, Jesus Christ...
...who, once and for all, consigned
that fallen tyrant to the flames of hell...
...who sent your only begotten son
into the world to crush that roaring lion...
...hasten to our call for help...
...and snatch from ruination and
from the clutches of the noonday devil...
...this human being,
made in your image and likeness.
Strike terror, Lord, into the beast
now laying waste to your vineyard.
Let your mighty hand cast him out
of your servant, Regan Teresa MacNeil...
[SCREAMING]
...so he may no longer hold captive
this person...
...whom it pleased you to make
in your image...
Aah!
MERRlN: ...and to redeem through your son,
who lives and reigns with you...
...in the unity of the Holy Spirit,
God, forever and ever.
-Amen.
-O Lord, hear my prayer.
[REGAN CRYlNG SLOWLY]
MERRlN:
Father Karras.
Damien. The response, please, Damien!
And let my cry come unto thee.
Almighty Lord, word of God the Father,
Jesus Christ...
...God and Lord of all creation...
[MOANING]
MERRlN:
...who gave to your holy apostles...
...the power to tramp underfoot
serpents and scorpions.
Grant me...
...your unworthy servant...
-...pardon for all my sins...
-Bastards!
...and the power to confront
this cruel demon.
[SCREAMING]
See the cross of the Lord.
Be gone, you hostile power.
-O Lord, hear my prayer.
-And let my cry come unto thee.
-The Lord be with you.
-And also with you.
[REGAN LAUGHlNG]
Father.
[COUGHING
I cast you out, unclean spirit!
-Shove it up your ass, you faggot!
-In the name of our Lord, Jesus Christ!
[RUMBLING]
It is he who commands you!
He who flung you straight from heaven
to the depths of hell!
-Fuck him!
-Be gone...
REGAN: Fuck him, Karras!
-...from this creature of God.
[GROWLS]
Be gone!
In the name of the Father,
and of the Son...
...and the Holy Spirit.
By this sign of the Holy Cross,
of our Lord Jesus Christ...
...who lives and reigns with the Father
and the Holy Spirit.
Damien!
Amen.
MERRlN:
God, defender of the human race...
[GASPS]
...look down in pity....
You killed your mother!
You left her alone to die!
-Shut up!
-She'll never forgive you!
KARRAS: Shut up!
REGAN: Bastard!
[REGAN GROANS]
MERRlN:
I command you...
...by the judge of the living
and the dead...
...to depart from this servant of God.
It's the power-- Holy water.
[RUMBLING]
MERRlN:
It's the power of Christ that compels you.
-The power of Christ compels you!
-The power of Christ compels you.
He brought you low
by his blood-stained cross!
Do not despise my command,
because you know me to be a sinner.
It is God himself who commands you.
The majestic Christ who commands you.
God, the Father, commands you.
[GROWLS]
God, the Son, commands you.
[YELLING]
God, the Holy Spirit, commands you.
The mystery of the cross commands you.
The blood of the martyrs commands you.
[MOANING]
MERRlN:
Give way to Christ, you prince of murderers.
You're guilty before almighty God.
Guilty before his son.
Guilty before the whole human race.
It is the Lord who expels you...
...he who is coming to judge both the living
and the dead and the world, by fire.
Are you tired?
Let's rest before we start again.
Why this girl? It doesn't make sense.
I think the point is to make us despair.
To see ourselves as...
...animal and ugly.
To reject the possibility that God
could love us.
Will you excuse me, Damien?
WOMAN:
Why? Why?
No. No.
[REGAN GROANING
[AS KARRAS' MOTHER]
Dimmy, why you do this to me?
Please, Dimmy. I'm afraid.
You're not my mother.
Dimmy, please!
MERRlN:
What is it?
Her heart.
Can you give her something?
KARRAS:
She'll go into a coma.
[SPEAKING IN GREEK]
You're not my mother!
MERRlN:
Don't listen.
Why, Dimmy?
Damien.
-Dimmy, please.
MERRlN: Damien.
Get out.
[GROWLS]
Our Father who art in heaven,
hallowed be thy name....
Is it over?
Mm-mm.
Is she gonna die?
No.
[DOORBELL BUZZES]
[GRUNTING
[GlGGLING lN DEMONIC VOlCE]
You son of a bitch!
[BOTH GRUNTING]
Take me.
Come into me.
Goddamn you, take me!
Take me!
[REGAN CRYlNG IN NORMAL VOICE]
[SCREAMING]
No!
REGAN:
Mother.
[SOBBlNG]
MAN 1 :
Did somebody fall?
MAN 2: The steps!
MAN 3: Help!
REGAN:
Mother!
[CRYING
Rags?
[SIRENS WAlLlNG]
[BOTH CRYING]
[CROWD CHATTERING]
Do you want to make your confession?
Are you sorry for--?
Are you sorry for having offended God
and for all the sins of your past life?
[SPEAKING IN LATIN
-Where do you want this?
-What?
Phonograph.
Storage.
That's everything.
I'm gonna miss you.
Same here.
Sure you won't change your mind?
I found this in her room.
You better hurry.
Come on, honey, we have to get going.
She doesn't remember any of it.
That's good.
-All done.
-Okay.
Honey, this is Father Dyer.
-Hi, Father.
-Hello.
Ready, missus.
-Goodbye, Father.
-Goodbye.
I'll call you.
Bye.
-Bye, Father.
-I hope l see you again.
I hope so too.
CHRIS:
Father Dyer?
I thought you'd like to keep this.
DYER:
Why don't you keep it?
Lieutenant.
You just missed them.
How's the girl?
She seemed fine.
That's important.
Well, well...
...back to business, back to work.
-Goodbye, Father.
-Goodbye.
Father Dyer...
...do you go to films?
Sure.
Well, I got passes.
In fact, l got a pass to the Crest
tomorrow night.
Would you like to go?
-What's playing?
-Wuthering Heights.
Who's in it?
Heathcliff, Jackie Gleason, and in the role
of Catherine Earnshaw, Lucille Ball.
I've seen it.
Another one.
-Had your lunch?
-No.
[ENGLISH - US - SDH]